<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Eduardo&#39;s Blog</title>
    <link>//localhost:1313/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Eduardo&#39;s Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 03:26:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="//localhost:1313/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Jazz_daredevil</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/ramblings/jazz_daredevil/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 03:26:37 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/ramblings/jazz_daredevil/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I was listening to Jon Benjamin&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Well, I Should Have&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; the other day and got to thinking on why I like it so much. Every time I hear it I can&amp;rsquo;t stop laughing, and not laughing because I think it&amp;rsquo;s funny, I laugh because I think it&amp;rsquo;s fun, and there&amp;rsquo;s a big difference (I think).&#xA;Well, I Should Have&amp;hellip; If you haven&amp;rsquo;t heard of this album, it&amp;rsquo;s a jazz album starred by Jon Benjamin, an American voice actor, who just so happens to be a piano player that has no clue whatsoever how to play piano.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Notes on Git</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/notes/git/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Aug 2024 03:15:38 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/notes/git/</guid>
      <description>1. Merging unrelated repos You can merge two entirely distinct and independent repos, which can be very useful. Saw this on one of Jon Gjenset&amp;rsquo;s streams where he basically has a repo with some general github actions for CI in rust crates, and whenever he creates a new repo for a crate, he adds the CI repo, merges it and gets all the github actions configured right away. The benefit of this strategy is that if somedat he updates the CI repo, adds some new action or changes an existing one, he can update any repo that uses them by just pulling and merging the changes.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Some Useful Commands</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/notes/useful-commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jul 2024 21:42:30 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/notes/useful-commands/</guid>
      <description>Here are some commands I don&amp;rsquo;t use all that often but still think are nice to remember just in case I need them:&#xA;watch -n [interval in seconds] [command] It runs the given command periodically (every 2 seconds by default) and prints the whole output to stdout.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I&#39;m 20!</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/ramblings/2o/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 21:50:23 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/ramblings/2o/</guid>
      <description>Basically what the title says, I&amp;rsquo;ve just turned 20 years old, and this is what&amp;rsquo;s on my mind. Stress runs in my family, and I am definetely guilty of worrying too much, too soon and too often about things. However, things have been looking up and I&amp;rsquo;ve found that lately I&amp;rsquo;ve gotten much better at not worrying unnecesseraly, and just having a good time even on weekdays, I hope that by the time I&amp;rsquo;m 21 I&amp;rsquo;ll have gotten even better at that.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Hello, World!</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/ramblings/hello/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 14:52:45 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/ramblings/hello/</guid>
      <description>This is my first rambling! These posts are meant to be informal, non-technical and low-quality short ramblings about me, my life, and what&amp;rsquo;s been on my mind lately.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>C macros</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/notes/eita/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jun 2024 14:39:56 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/notes/eita/</guid>
      <description>A collection of useful or interesting c macros I&amp;rsquo;ve collected </description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How to solve any dynamic programming problem</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/dynamic-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:01:33 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/dynamic-programming/</guid>
      <description>Dynamic programming is a scary name, but once you understand their general structure of these problems, they become much easier to solve. But first, what is dynamic programming? Dynamic programming is the discipline of solving combinatorial optimization problems as efficiently as possible, without having to calculate every possible solution. In technical terms, an optimal solution is any solution which maximizes (or minimizes) the target function (what we want to optmize). There is a 3 step process to solving any DP problem:</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Reading C Source Code: SDS</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/sds-source-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Feb 2024 10:48:46 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/sds-source-code/</guid>
      <description>Reading source code can be a great way to learn from those who have more experience, as well as see how the projects are structured, how functions are written, etc. So today we are going to be diving in the sds source code. Sds stands for simple dynamic strings, and it&amp;rsquo;s a three file library for dealing with dynamic strings in c, most notably, it&amp;rsquo;s used inside Redis for everything pertaining to strings.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My First Open Source Contribution</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/my-first-open-source-contribution/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2023 14:47:56 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/my-first-open-source-contribution/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday my first ever PR to an open source project was accepted and commited, however, my contribution had (almost) nothing to do with code, but instead documentation, and I&amp;rsquo;m perfectly fine with that, here&amp;rsquo;s why.&#xA;I&amp;rsquo;m relatively new to programming, in fact, my journey into coding started less than 2 years ago, when I got into university and started my undergrad in computer science and engineering. Since then I&amp;rsquo;ve had basically one coding discipline per semester (the first 2 years are kind of slow since I have to take a lot of engineering disciplines such as physics (1 to 4), a lot of maths and just a bit of chemistry).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>TIL How To Setup Multiple Git Accounts</title>
      <link>//localhost:1313/posts/setup-multiple-git-accounts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 20:15:41 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>//localhost:1313/posts/setup-multiple-git-accounts/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m part of a junior company at my university where we design websites and web apps for small businesses. To keep everything neat and tidy, everyone gets an email account associated to the company (just like a company email minus the part where I get paid) to use all our tools such as figma for prototyping, google drive for file and document storage, and most importantly github for developing and maintaining projects.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
